<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>The dissenting casuist, or, The second part of a dialogue between prejudice, a dissenting country gentleman, and reason, a student in the university being I. a clear justification of the execution of the laws against dissenters, II. a comparison of the arguments on both sides concerning monarchy in general, III. concerning an elective kingdom, or whether a lawful successor or true heir upon any misdemeanours may be excluded.</title>
            <author>Wood, Thomas, 1661-1722.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1682</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 77 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 20 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2013-12">2013-12 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A66942</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing W3409</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R21026</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">12737405</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">ocm 12737405</idno>
            <idno type="VID">93024</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A66942)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 93024)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 994:21)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>The dissenting casuist, or, The second part of a dialogue between prejudice, a dissenting country gentleman, and reason, a student in the university being I. a clear justification of the execution of the laws against dissenters, II. a comparison of the arguments on both sides concerning monarchy in general, III. concerning an elective kingdom, or whether a lawful successor or true heir upon any misdemeanours may be excluded.</title>
                  <author>Wood, Thomas, 1661-1722.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[4], 35 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed for T. Sawbridge ...,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1682.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in Huntington Library.</note>
                  <note>Attributed to Thomas Wood. cf. NUC pre-1956.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Church of England --  Clergy.</term>
               <term>Church and state --  Great Britain.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2012-04</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-04</date>
            <label>Apex CoVantage</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-05</date>
            <label>Pip Willcox</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-05</date>
            <label>Pip Willcox</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-02</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:93024:1"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:93024:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>THE Diſſenting Caſuiſt: OR, THE SECOND PART OF A DIALOGUE BETWEEN <hi>PREJ<g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>DICE, a Diſſenting Country Gentleman,</hi> AND <hi>REASON, a Student in the <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>niverſity.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>BEING
<list>
                  <item>I. A clear Juſtification of the Execution of the Laws againſt Diſſenters.</item>
                  <item>II. A Compariſon of the Arguments on both ſides concerning Monarchy in general.</item>
                  <item>III. Concerning an Elective Kingdom, or whether a Lawful Suc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſor or true Heir upon any Miſdemeanours may be excluded.</item>
               </list>
            </p>
            <q>Saepe etiam Stultus opportuna loquitur.</q>
            <p>
               <hi>LONDON,</hi> Printed for <hi>T. Sawbridge,</hi> at the Three Flower de Luces in <hi>Little Britain.</hi> 1682.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="to_the_reader">
            <pb facs="tcp:93024:2"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:93024:2"/>
            <head>TO THE READER.</head>
            <p>THE firſt Part of this Dialogue (being not above three Sheets) was deſigned onely by way of <hi>Pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>face</hi> to this; I being forced to dig upon <hi>Rubbiſh,</hi> be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore I could come to their <hi>Mine of Gold:</hi> but really if you are impartial, you will conclude with me, that this is mere <hi>Rubbiſh</hi> too. If in the firſt Part they were re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſented as <hi>groſs Fools,</hi> they muſt thank themſelves for it, not me. If people talk <hi>idlely,</hi> I cannot help it: I am ſure if you will take the pains to keep them company, you may hear the ſame every day. But <hi>Uglineſs</hi> does not care to have its Picture drawn. I am no common Pam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phlettier, neither do I at all delight in it; being very well ſatisfied in my Conſcience, that the Works of our <hi>Tribe</hi> will never be ſent to Forein Courts, or tranſlated into an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>other Language: I believe it is with most of them as it is with the Poets, they firſt get the Itch of writing in their Fingers, (being perhaps an Infection from the Pen they hold) and then it preſently ſpreads over their whole Bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dies, ſo that they can never be at quiet till they are <hi>ſcratch<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing upon Paper.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>My deſign is onely for the good of my Country; but if I ſignifie but little toward it, my Zele and Loyalty will be commended.</p>
            <pb facs="tcp:93024:3"/>
            <p>This Diſcourſe is not levelled againſt any particular man, but againſt all their Arguments that <hi>have been, are at preſent,</hi> or <hi>are to come;</hi> and that is a bold word you will ſay, but <hi>read and judge.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>I have engaged with their Champions, condeſcended to <hi>the little ones,</hi> and reſolving (as much as in me lieth) to clear the Country of all ſorts of Vermin, I have div'd into <hi>Stews, Haylofts,</hi> and <hi>Boghouſes.</hi> If I have not been very exact in my Quotations on the Margin, I ſuppoſe every Author can find his own words out. I am ſure I have not abus'd or miſinterpreted his Aſsertions. Pardon pray the Printers <hi>Errata,</hi> and I am</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>Your very Humble Servant, T. W.</signed>
               <date>June 20. 1682.</date>
            </closer>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="dialogue">
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:93024:3"/>
            <head>The Diſſenting CASUIST: OR, The Second Part of a Dialogue between <hi>Prejudice</hi> a Diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſenting Countrey Gentleman, and <hi>Reaſon</hi> a Student in the Univerſity, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
            </head>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Prej.</speaker>
               <p>Come, Sir, I am deſirous of entring into a ſecond Diſcourſe with you; the Diſtraction of the Times makes me thoughtful, ſo that I find I am forc'd by my Conſcience and good Nature to raiſe up as many Arguments as is fit and convenient for a man in my mean capacity. I keep ſeveral Perſons in pay, ſending them out to Taverns, Coffee-houſes, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> to ſee if there is any thing more to be <hi>glean'd</hi> and pic'kd up towards the main<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tenance of our Cauſe, and the heartning on of the Righte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous, that they may not have reaſon to ſay, they are wea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry of theſe <note n="*" place="margin">Sh—— Sh——te</note> 
                  <hi>Carryings</hi> on. And truly I think my ſelf as Loyal as he that keeps a Regiment of Souldiers at his own charge, and is hourly at his Majeſties Service. Well then, firſt, I ſay you <hi>Crape Gown-men</hi> are rank Papiſts, down<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>right <hi>Devils,</hi> though you hide your <hi>cloven Feet,</hi> though for the preſent you are pleas'd to put on the Garments of the <hi>Angels of Light.</hi> Your Pride, Ambition, Covetouſneſs, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> ſhew that you are <hi>poſſeſs'd.</hi> The Reſtauration of the Abbey Lands, and the pretended Riches of the Church, Cardinals Caps, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> the dear embraces of the gaudy painted Whore, are the Objects of your furious and extravagant Loyalty. Your Covetouſneſs is ſo great, and <note n="*" place="margin">
                     <hi>A Scan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dalous Li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bel call'd</hi> Speculum Crape-Gownorum <hi>Part.</hi> 2.</note> 
                  <hi>there is ſuch a uume<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rous Fry of you, that hunger and thirſt after Maintenance, and ſo few bones in the Nation, that you ſnarl at all who do but pretend to ſhare with you.</hi> We may eaſily diſcern whether
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:93024:4"/> the Good Pious Nonconformiſt Miniſters, or the Prieſts of <hi>Baal,</hi> are the trueſt <hi>Levites,</hi> or the <hi>choſen of the Lord;</hi> the Actions of the former being wholly, and without the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſideration of worldly Gain, directed to the <hi>Spiritual edifi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cation and recovery of Souls, to the preaching of the Lord Chriſt, &amp;c.</hi> whereas the Zeal and Divinity of the latter muſt never <hi>mount</hi> or <hi>fly abroad,</hi> unleſs it be upon <hi>Wings</hi> that are adorned with <hi>ſilver</hi> and <hi>golden Feathers,</hi> unleſs for every Scripture Sentence ſo much Money is paid down as may recover the Preachers Spirits, render him in good <hi>Plight,</hi> that he may come up with the greater Aſſurance and Eagerneſs the next Week.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Reaſ.</speaker>
               <p>I do not underſtand what you mean by all this <hi>Ribble Rabble,</hi> unleſs (that in your Judgment) 'tis a thing unbecoming and irreligious, that our Miniſters do not preach, and perform their Spiritual Offices in any place, without a Promiſed Maintenance and Salary, or without Reſpect to things that are ſordid and temporal. I am ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry far different from this Opinion, or do in no wiſe think it unbecoming, or that a care for a competency of living deſerves the Epithet of <hi>Sordid.</hi> We know that Mens Minds are now grown more carnal and ſenſual than ever, that really Chriſts Kingdom is not of this World, nor in the Hearts of <hi>worldly</hi> men; that <q rend="margQuotes">"Intereſt and Riches is the only God ador'd here, that the Man that can ſhew a good Face, and an Acquittance for ſo much Money, ſhall gain more Reſpect and Honour than Virtue it ſelf if ſhe be <hi>naked.</hi>
                  </q> Alas! we have very few Philoſophers amongſt us that will admire Wiſdom in her <hi>Rags.</hi> A Knaviſh <hi>Maho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>met</hi> if he ſets in a <hi>Throne</hi> ſhall gain more Followers than a True Chriſt if he once lay in a Manger. Men will ſcarce be convinc'd by the Doctrine of that Perſon who does owe him Money, or who is beholding to him for his Bread. 'Tis very requiſite, yea and neceſſary, that they ſhould be endowed with the greateſt Plenty both of Riches and Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour;
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:93024:4"/> Firſt, becauſe as I told you, it gains them a greater Reſpect from their Auditors, who on this Conſideration will more eaſily yield up their Hearts and Attention. Se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>condly, becauſe there will be greater Encouragements, where they may not be liable to ill Fortune, and the Croſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes and many Accidents of the World, or have their Stu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dies interrupted, or that glorious deſign of making men eternally happy, ſwallowed up in Poverty. We often ſee what Authority the Preſence of a <hi>Biſhop</hi> has over his vaſt Congregation; whilſt perhaps the <hi>Poor Curate</hi> is attended only by a few ſerving Maids, and very drowzily hearken'd to, though perhaps his Doctrine may be the ſame, or eve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry whit as good. In my ſmall reading I have found that heretofore <note n="*" place="margin">Juſtin.</note> 
                  <hi>Idem fuit Rex &amp; Sacerdos,</hi> and that many like <hi>Aaron</hi> have almoſt went hand in hand with the <hi>Moſes</hi> or ſupreme Magiſtrate. I would not have you think by any means, that I am willing they ſhould be encourag'd to Luxury, or an ignoble Eaſe, or be pamper'd in any Vice; for, I ſuppoſe all this while if they ſhould not have the diſcretion to manage themſelves according to the ſtrict Rules of Morality and Chriſtianity, that there is a King and a Power above 'em, that will ſee they ſhall be other<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe diſpoſed of. If men were truly judicious, and would reſpect them merely for their Function, there would be no need of theſe <hi>external Daubings</hi> to ſet them off, none of theſe <hi>gildings on our Altars.</hi>
               </p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Prejud.</speaker>
               <p>Methinks they ſhould be contented with the<note place="margin">Spec. Crap. p. 6.</note> 
                  <hi>Tithes</hi> of <hi>
                     <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nity, Love,</hi> and <hi>Charity.</hi>
               </p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Reaſ.</speaker>
               <p>Yes, if men would give it them, I am ſure they would then rejoyce as much in Self-denial and Want, (although I ſuppoſe a Self-denial in their Affluence too) and think themſelves as great as they poſſibly could in all their Glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ries. I am ſure you will not think I can have any other deſign than to ſpeak my Judgment and Opinion. I am aſham'd to ſee a reverend grey-headed man, profound in
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:93024:5"/> Learning, exact in Morality and pureſt Piety, after many years toil and labour, become onely a Chaplain to a <hi>toyiſh</hi> Lord; and then to be thruſt up in a Garret, ſet at the lower end of the Table, riſe at ſecond courſe, and be thought onely fit company for the Steward and Butler. I confeſs it might be more pardonable thus to uſe a <hi>young, raw, ſloven<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly</hi> Fellow, who has crept into the Clergy unawares, whoſe mean Education and Dulneſs may ſomewhat deſerve this; yet methinks they ſhould not chooſe a perſon, whoſe Of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fice is ſo ſacred, for Formality ſake, or that they may have occaſion ſometime or other to deride him. The Supercili<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouſneſs of theſe Patrons make the Clergy ſo much deſpis'd, and the name of <hi>Parſon</hi> to become ſo ſcandalous. They do it that they may be more ſecurely debauch'd, and exalt themſelves thus, that it may be thought impudence in <hi>the Fellow that ſays Grace</hi> to adviſe or recall them. Their wi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſer Anceſtors did think it Preferment and Honour to enter into that Sacred Office; whereas theſe being fooliſhly aſha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med of it, make us guilty of <hi>Jeroboams</hi> ſin, and for the<note place="margin">1 Kings 13. 33.</note> moſt part force us to take in the meaneſt of the People. If you would throughly weigh theſe things, you would be far from having them ſtript of what they have, or that they ſhould follow the pretended ſelf-denyal of the Saints, but that rather they ſhould be higher advanced and ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>noured.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Prejud.</speaker>
               <p>This Courtier-like way of yours, in ſtanding upon theſe Punctilio's Honour, this impatiency of Af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fronts, ſhews that your Minds are tied to your carnal Hearts, that Honour and Preferment is your onely aim. The meekneſs of our Brethren, their Philoſophical neglect of the World, will teach and inſtruct you otherwiſe. They think themſelves as Servants to all, and know that by being the leaſt, they do become the greateſt; that if they themſelves do not provide Scrip and Shooes, it will be provided for them.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <pb n="5" facs="tcp:93024:5"/>
               <speaker>Reaſ.</speaker>
               <p>
                  <note place="margin">Apology for Ninconfor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſt Mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtry.</note> I underſtand you cannot or will not ſee ſo far as other men. Mr. <hi>Baxter</hi> very proudly tells you, he refu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed a Biſhoprick, and confeſſeth he hath ſo good natur'd and ſo kind a Flock already under him, who allowed him a very <hi>competent and large</hi> Maintainance. They are for pulling down Biſhopricks, and for dividing Inheritances, that all of them, who are now excluded as Rebels and Traytors, may then come in for a ſhare. Their ſin of ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>parating from us, as I ſhall prove to you anon, is <hi>wilful and devilliſh;</hi> 
                  <note place="margin">Ibid.</note> and if ſo, according to their own Confeſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, common Drunkards, Swearers, Fornicators, are rather to be tolerated in a Commonwealth. Do you think that theſe have <hi>the ſpirit of meekneſs</hi> in them, or the leaſt ſpark of true Piety, who flie in the faces of the Kings Officers, when they come to diſturb their ſeditious and diſloyal Meetings; contend with them as if 'twas their Inheritance, openly defie Heaven and the Ordinance of an Onipotent God? <q rend="margQuotes">"Not but that an Aſs reſiſteth his Maſter as much by ſtanding ſtill or running back, as if he had kick'd at him.</q> If their Conſcience tells them they muſt needs preach, and by no means hide their Talent, if diſpenſing the Word is their onely aim, let them go and plant the Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpel amongſt the <hi>Indians,</hi> where perhaps there will be no Authority to reſiſt, no commiſſion of ſuch deadly ſins. But they object and ſay, they do not underſtand their <hi>Language,</hi> and if they ſhould try at it, they could arrive but half<note place="margin">Ibid.</note> way, ſpeak it imperfectly and very diſorderly, which would be apt to procure <hi>deriſion</hi> and <hi>diſesteem.</hi> What do theſe <hi>deep ſanctified holy men</hi> ſtart at ſuch trivial things, who profeſs themſelves ready every minute to undergo Impriſonment and Death for the <hi>Name of the Lord Jeſus?</hi> Away, 'tis ſuch nonſenſe and ill arguing that a <hi>Boy</hi> may diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cover it. I believe we muſt think of a <hi>Penſylvania</hi> for them too, and ſhip them off by the next fair Wind. I am as much againſt Perſecution as any man; there is no one
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:93024:6"/> pitieth the poor Proteſtants in <hi>France</hi> more than I do; but I am far from calling the execution of the Laws againſt our Diſſenters <hi>Perſecution,</hi> yea it is a thing neceſſary and commendable, without which true Piety can never flou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſh, nor Church and State ever be at quiet. Thoſe in <hi>France</hi> were called by their King, <hi>the meek, the willing, the best Subjects in the world,</hi> as if he was ſorry his Religion forced him to ſuch hard uſage; whereas of our falſe <hi>Proteſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ants</hi> it has been long ago declared, that they are <hi>a perverſe generation,</hi> and that for Subjects <hi>'tis impoſſible to have worſe.</hi> Believe it Sir, 'tis true as a Good Divine has ſaid before<note place="margin">Dr. Sprat Serm. Apr. 20, 82.</note> me, <hi>There is ſcarce any one that adheres to this Party, but either he, or ſome of his near Relations, have been al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ready forgiven; they carry about with them the black guilt, not onely of Rebellion, but of an ungrateful Rebellion after Pardon received: A ſin which the Devil himſelf is not capable of committing.</hi>
               </p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Prejud.</speaker>
               <p>Sir, I will not believe one word what you ſay; but pray did not <hi>Peter</hi> and <hi>Paul</hi> preach the Goſpel though<note place="margin">Baxt. Apol.</note> they were forbidden by the <hi>Jews</hi> that were in Authority? I tell you, if their Conſcience aſſures them that they are in the right, and that they muſt preach the Goſpel, the Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thority of Kings and Emperours to the contrary ſignifi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth nothing: <hi>We muſt obey God rather than Man.</hi>
               </p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Reaſ.</speaker>
               <p>We muſt obey God in a good cauſe rather than Man in a bad one; but if we can obey God and Man too, and do not, we are in a very deſperate condition. But S. <hi>Peter</hi> and <hi>Paul</hi> knew and had <hi>aſſurance</hi> from the imme<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diate hand of God, that it was his will that they ſhould preach the Goſpel, and that the Commands of the <hi>Jews</hi> were in no wiſe to be obeyed. But I cannot ſee how this Inſtance pleads for you, who have no ſuch aſſurance and command to reſiſt Authority. And that you have no ſuch manifeſt aſſurance, that you cannot pretend <hi>Conſcience</hi> in this caſe, that your ſin of ſeparating from us is <hi>wilful</hi> and
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:93024:6"/> 
                  <hi>deviliſh,</hi> and <hi>ill natur'd,</hi> as I promiſed you a little before, I ſhall come now to prove it. I ſuppoſe you are not igno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rant that Conſcience is divided into three parts.</p>
               <p>Firſt, into a <hi>gainſaying</hi> or <hi>reſolved Conſcience.</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Biſhop San<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſon.</note>
               </p>
               <p>Secondly, into a <hi>ſcrupulous Conſcience.</hi> And,</p>
               <p>Thirdly, into a <hi>doubtful Conſcience.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>I mean by a <hi>reſolved</hi> or <hi>gainſaying Conſcience,</hi> a <hi>Conſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence</hi> where there is true grounds, plain and manifeſt Texts of Scripture to back it on, or plead for it. Now that Diſſenters cannot ſay 'tis out of this Conſcience they reſiſt, that they cannot ſhew any true grounds, any manifeſt and plain Texts of Scripture, I ſhall ſay no more but appeal to their Writings, and to the whole World, if it be not true; Whether this their grand Reaſon, <hi>We muſt obey God rather than Man,</hi> does determine whether the thing com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>manded is <hi>lawful</hi> or <hi>not lawful,</hi> whether it is enough to make a reſolved or gainſaying Conſcience, or is any true Argument for their Nonconformity.</p>
               <p>A <hi>ſcrupulous Conſcience</hi> is that where the <hi>Conſcience</hi> does <hi>incline</hi> one way, where it is not fully reſolved, and in <hi>every particular</hi> ſatisfied, as being built only upon Proba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bilities.</p>
               <p>A <hi>doubtful Conſcience</hi> is that where the Scales hang even, without inclining one way or the other, ſo as the weak and fickle man cannot well reſolve which way he ſhould take.</p>
               <p>Be therefore in either of theſe the <hi>Nonconforming Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcience,</hi> why I ſay the Injunction of Authority does over<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rule either of them. I will give you advantage in an Exam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple; Suppoſe a Prince commandeth his Subjects to ſerve in<note place="margin">Ibid.</note> a War that is unjuſt, where there may appear to the un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſtanding of the Subject great likelihoods of ſuch Inju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtice; why I ſay for all this the Subject is bound to fight in this quarrel, nay he is deep in Diſloyalty and Treaſon if he refuſe the Service, whatſoever pretenſions of Conſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:93024:7"/> he makes for ſuch a refuſal. And this I am confident you your ſelves will acknowledge. Neither need he trou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble himſelf that he ſhall bring the guilt of innocent bloud upon his head, for the bloud that is unrighteouſly ſhed in that Quarrel, he muſt anſwer that ſet him to work, not he that ſpilt it. And truly it is a great wonder to me, (I ſpeak it without paſſion) that men that are able to weigh the force of Precepts and Reaſons, that bind Inferiours to yield obedience to Superiours, ſhould be ſo nonſenſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cal and irrational, as to be otherwiſe minded in our caſe, which is of the like nature. When there is a certainty and an uncertainty, we muſt let the uncertainty go, and cleave to that which is certain. The <hi>general</hi> Rule is cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain, that we muſt obey the Magiſtrate in all things not con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trary to the will of God; but the <hi>particular</hi> is uncertain, whether Conformity commanded by the Magiſtrate be con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trary to the will of God or no, (I ſay 'tis uncertain with you, becauſe I ſuppoſe you are <hi>ſcrupulous</hi> and <hi>doubtful</hi> of it.) Wherefore I ſay, if you cleave to an uncertainty be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore a certainty, perſiſt in Nonconformity, uncertain with you whether lawful, rather than to a certain and poſitive Command of <hi>ſubmitting to Superiours;</hi> I ſay you ſhew your ſelves to be wilfully blind, wilfully irrational, your ſin to be <hi>devilliſh</hi> and <hi>ill natur'd,</hi> the Propoſition that I was to prove.</p>
               <p>Good God! that the Apoſtle ſhould command thee po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſitively and plainly to obey <hi>for conſcience ſake,</hi> and thou ſhouldſt infer from hence, that thou ſhouldſt diſobey <hi>for conſcience ſake</hi> too. That you ſhould <hi>ſubmit your ſelves to</hi>
                  <note place="margin">1 Pe. 2. 13, 16.</note> 
                  <hi>every Ordinance of Man for the Lords ſake: As free, and not uſing your liberty for a cloke of maliciouſneſs,</hi> is the ear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſt deſire of S. <hi>Peter</hi> and God himſelf.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Prejud.</speaker>
               <p>But, Sir, for all your haſte; if you affirm that an <hi>uncertainty</hi> and a thing <hi>controvertible,</hi> (the Supreme Pow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er determining the caſe) does find the Subject not to diſpute
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:93024:7"/> the Authority or his Obedience; I ſay you are in a miſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>take. For all thoſe Articles of Faith, as Worſhipping Ima<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ges,<note place="margin">Charge of the Tory Plot main<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tained, p. 4.</note> Tranſubſtantiation, &amp;c. are controvertible, und uncer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain, and in diſpute between us and the Papiſts; but though the Authority of Angels ſhould command me to believe and comform to theſe things, I ought not to do it.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Reaſ.</speaker>
               <p>You muſt underſtand me in things <hi>indifferent</hi> in the matter of Ceremonies, and the like, where the Conſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence does not <hi>gainſay,</hi> and is not otherwiſe <hi>reſolved.</hi> Now that I ſhould not conſent to the Worſhipping of Images and Tranſubſtantiation, &amp;c. I have clear poſitive proof, the one being expreſly forbidden in the ſecond Command<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, the other in a clear Text of Scripture, and being repugnant to my Senſes and common Reaſon. And this is the ſenſe of the <note n="*" place="margin">Mr. L'E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrange.</note> Author, whom the Pamphlettier pretends to bring to an Abſurdity, being firſt pleaſed to miſtake his meaning.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Prejud.</speaker>
               <p>I have met and read of Arguments, that ſeem to make it out, that our Diſſenting Brethren act in all things according to Divine Truth; that the Execution of the Laws is a downright injury, abominable injuſtice and perſecuti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on. And though I have ſcrap'd them out of a ſcandalous Libel, they ſeem to be pretty tolerable. Firſt he ſays, that<note place="margin">Spec. Crape.</note> the generality of the Diſſenters are good men, and that they fully anſwer the deſcription of a good man, <hi>Pſalm</hi> 15. that is, they behave themſelves dutifully and obediently towards the Civil Magiſtrate, and juſtly towards their Neighbours. And though perhaps he cannot juſtifie every individual perſon, nevertheleſs he hopes you will not be ſo imprudent as to throw a whole Quarter of <hi>Wheat</hi> away, for the mixture of a Peck of <hi>Tares.</hi>
               </p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Reaſ.</speaker>
               <p>The whole Body of them reſiſt and murmur at the Authority that commands them to raiſe their Meetings, and therefore how can you have the impudence to ſay, they are dutiful and obedient toward the Civil Magiſtrate?</p>
               <pb n="10" facs="tcp:93024:8"/>
               <p>One ſwears the <hi>D.</hi> of <hi>Y.</hi> is a Traytor, that he fired the City, nay that the King himſelf had a hand in it; makes it his buſineſs to undervalue men, and undo them in their Credits, giving out that they are broken and bankrupt, &amp;c. Another that was formerly a Crony to S. <hi>Stephen</hi> ſends<note place="margin">B. the Hop<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>merchant.</note> 
                  <hi>Hop Poles</hi> to be turned into <hi>Proteſtant Flails,</hi> drinks to the Memory of a pious Traytor, and nothing but <hi>Bloud and Wouuds</hi> if the Company refuſes it. Then there is an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>other with a long Chin ſwears all the Biſhops are Papiſts, and that he in time will ſtrip them of their Lawn Sleeves, and make them look as ridiculous as ſo many <hi>Jack Daws</hi> without their Feathers. And here's one that being weary of ſecret Faction, comes forth boldly, and proſecutes peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple at Law for <hi>Scandalum Magnatum,</hi> and then if he thinks he has vex'd and tormented them, he will go no further, will let fall his Suit, and for half a minute be at quiet. He grins like a Dog, and in the evening walketh about the City, and like a Lion ſeeketh whom he may de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vour. Here is a Company ſent to Taverns and Coffee Houſes to diſpute the <hi>caſe,</hi> to blow the Coals with a ſtron<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger Breath, and if it be poſſible to make it flame out. Theſe are to make Bonfires, raiſe Tumults, and as if it were a perpetual <hi>Whitſun Ale,</hi> they ſtop every Paſſenger, force him to drink a Health to <hi>My Lord</hi> — and <hi>The good old Cauſe</hi> his <hi>Lady.</hi> And will any one make me believe, that theſe are not <hi>Juglers, Baxters,</hi> and <hi>Owens,</hi> and <hi>Humble Moderators, &amp;c.</hi> behind the Curtain, that guide theſe <hi>Pup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>petae</hi> by a ſecret Spring, and ſend them <hi>dancing</hi> into the world?</p>
               <p>A Conventicle in ſhort is a Nurſery for <hi>pack'd Juries, Injuſtice,</hi> and <hi>Rebellion;</hi> and to invert what you ſay, a Quarter of <hi>Tares,</hi> and ſcarce a Handful of <hi>Wheat</hi> in it.</p>
               <p>But if there ſhould be any good men, any <hi>Gouges</hi> now<note place="margin">See the Tryal of Char. I. his Judges.</note> alive amongſt them, they muſt fare as ſome of our late Kings fooliſh Judges, who were onely Hearers, and did
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:93024:8"/> ſit onely for Company, but were hang'd (though againſt their wills) for Company too.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Prejud.</speaker>
               <p>But the man ſays, they do exerciſe according to the Liturgy of the Church of <hi>England.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>The Liturgy of the Church of <hi>England</hi> contains no more<note place="margin">Spec. Crape.</note> than onely Truth; The Diſſenters ſpeak and pray accord<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing to Truth: <hi>Ergo</hi> —</p>
               <p>The firſt Propoſition you your ſelves will grant, for if the Liturgy contains any thing beſides Truth, it contains a Lie, &amp;c. which you will never own. And then that the Diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſenters preach nothing but Truth, nay the Truth of Truth, Divine Truth all the world will grant.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Reaſ.</speaker>
               <p>No, I my ſelf will never grant it. I will ſhew you a Book called <hi>The Diſſenters Sayings</hi> one of theſe days, where if you don't find their Doctrien to be faith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fully collected, and in them curſed Lies, the Lies of Lies, Holliſh Lies, I will be contented to take that puniſhment upon me, which the Diſſenters deſerve. But as to the Argument, the Author ſhews he had forgot his Logick at this time; there be two <hi>Brethren</hi> of it, and very much like it in another Author: If Impotency be a ſufficient<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Tory Plot, p.</hi> 15. &amp; 19.</note> cauſe for diſſolving the ſacred tie of Marriage, becauſe the main end of Marriage, the propagating Mankind, is there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by fruſtrated; it may be equally reaſonable to debar the <hi>D. of Y.</hi> the <hi>Eſpouſal</hi> (a pretty Conceit) of the Govern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, who is perverted to an utter incapacity of anſwer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the ends of it. Again; If a Papiſt can exclude (un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lawfully) a Proteſtant, a Proteſtant may (unlawfully) ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clude a Papiſt. And of another Author, whom I have for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>got at preſent, that would prove the <hi>Scripture</hi> not to be the <hi>Word of God,</hi> becauſe the <hi>Word</hi> was made <hi>Fleſh: Ergo</hi> —</p>
               <p>This by the by; now to the main point. If the Litur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gy contains nothing but Truth, they that ſpeak and pray according to Truth, ſpeak and pray according to the Li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turgy. If this Glaſs contains nothing but Wine, he that
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:93024:9"/> drinks up the Wine ſwallows down the Glaſs. Look up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on your Argument a ſecond time, and tell me if you dare that there is Conſequence in it. A man that ſtands upon <hi>Bow Steeple,</hi> and repeats the Commandments, that preaches. Chriſt and him crucified, in High-ways and Ditches, ſpeaks and prays according to Truth; yet notwithſtanding this perſon ſhall be look'd upon as irregular and prophane, and puniſh'd accordingly. In ſhort, the Liturgy of the Church of <hi>England</hi> is a certain <hi>Form</hi> and <hi>Manner</hi> agreed upon by Authority for the better <hi>
                     <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>tterance of the Truth,</hi> and therefore he onely that acts according to this <hi>Form</hi> and <hi>Manner,</hi> comes to Church, &amp;c. does act according to the Liturgy of the Church of <hi>England.</hi>
               </p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Prejud.</speaker>
               <p>Sir, this is an Argument that we have cheriſhed for theſe many years, and I am ſure 'tis impoſſible for you to confute it in ſo ſhort a time as you pretend to do.</p>
               <p>We loſe our Chriſtian Liberty if we muſt be forced to obey this <hi>Form.</hi> We loſe our Chriſtian Liberty, when by Human Laws things indifferent are determined either the one way or the other: Now Ceremonies and Liturgy are indifferent things, if they were not determined by Authority; And why Eccleſiaſtical Conſtitutions ſhould<note place="margin">1 Arg.</note> determine us preciſely to one ſide in the uſe of indifferent things, which God and Chriſt have left free, I know no Reaſon.</p>
               <p>By inducing a neceſſity upon the thing they enjoyn,<note place="margin">2 Arg.</note> they take upon them to alter the nature of things, and make that to become neceſſary which is indifferent, which God onely can do.</p>
               <p>It makes theſe indifferent things of abſolute neceſſity un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to<note place="margin">3 Arg.</note> Salvation, foraſmuch as it is neceſſary to Salvation to do that which he is bound in Conſcience to do, (and you ſay we muſt in Conſcience obey Superiours;) ſo that by this device <hi>Surplice, Organs, Kneeling at the Communion, Bowing at the Name of Jeſus, &amp;c.</hi> are neceſſary to Sal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vation.
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:93024:9"/> I ſay, all this is a grand Impoſition upon Chriſtian Liberty.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Reaſ.</speaker>
               <p>I will anſwer theſe Arguments with as much bre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vity as I can, and abſtract from the large Diſcourſe which Biſhop <hi>Sanderſon</hi> affords you.</p>
               <p>To the firſt Argument I anſwer, That the determining of any thing <hi>in unam partem,</hi> taketh not away a mans Li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>berty. For the Liberty of a Chriſtian to any thing in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>different<note place="margin">Biſhop San<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſon.</note> conſiſteth in this, that his <hi>Judgment</hi> is thorowly perſuaded of the indifferency of it; and therefore 'tis the determination of the Judgment in the <hi>Opinion</hi> of the thing, not in the <hi>
                     <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ſe</hi> of it, that taketh away Chriſtian Li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>berty. For Example: If my Friend invite me to Supper, ſhall I not promiſe him to come, becauſe the Liberty I had before to go or not go will be determined by making ſuch a Promiſe? It is a very vain <hi>power</hi> and <hi>indifferency,</hi> that may not be brought into <hi>act</hi> or <hi>actually determined;</hi> but God made no <hi>power</hi> in vain, as is long ago agreed up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on both by Philoſophers and Divines.</p>
               <p>To the ſecond Argument I anſwer, That the <hi>nature</hi> of the thing enjoyned is not changed, but ſtill <hi>indifferent;</hi> though for ſome conveniences there is an <hi>Order</hi> to uſe them added to that Indifferency.</p>
               <p>To the third, 'Tis the <hi>Obedience</hi> that is neceſſary to Sal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vation, as being immediately commanded by God, and not the <hi>things commanded,</hi> for they are ſtill indifferent. A Maſter commands his Servant to go to Market, or wear a Livery, the Servant is bound in Conſcience to obey his Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſter; but his going to Market, or his wearing a Livery, the things ſuppoſed to be commanded, by every one muſt be concluded to be indifferent, and not at all neceſſary to Salvation.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Prejud.</speaker>
               <p>'Tis Popiſh to ſay, Humane Laws bind the Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcience as much as Divine.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <pb n="14" facs="tcp:93024:10"/>
               <speaker>Reaſ.</speaker>
               <p>The Papiſts teach this Doctrien not onely in re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpect of the <hi>Obedience,</hi> but of the <hi>things commanded;</hi> which we do onely in reſpect of the <hi>Obedience.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>I would deſire again, that our Diſſenters would conſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der, whether the pretence of a purer Religion, or the loſs of Chriſtian Liberty or Conſcience, will excuſe them. <hi>Corah</hi>'s Rebellion was upon theſe pretences, and though he<note place="margin">Numb. 6.</note> was not actually in Arms, but did onely <hi>aſſociate</hi> againſt and ſeparate from the Government, yet God puniſhed him with a moſt ſevere death.</p>
               <p>Again, our Ceremonies and Methods were agreed upon<note place="margin">Sir William Smiths Speech, De. 5. 1981</note> by a Parliament, had the conſent of both King and Peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple. Which when I have ſeriouſly thought on, raiſed my admiration, how any man can think himſelf hardly dealt with, when he is required to comply to that, to which he had before conſented: or that he ſhould think it reaſona<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble that ſeparate Aſſemblies or publick Conventicles, ſhould be permitted in oppoſition to the eſtabliſh'd Government. I cannot underſtand it otherwiſe, but that theſe perſons who frequent Conventicles, and give themſelves up to be rul'd and directed by their Teachers, allow theſe Teachers both Infallibility and Supremacy; and not onely ſo, but alſo a Legiſlative Power, to make what Orders they think fit, which is indeed to loſe your Chriſtian Liberty, and to make a Prince and a Pope in every Congregation. Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſides, theſe publick Conventicles proclaim our Diviſions to the world, diſcover our weakneſſes, and muſt needs cauſe a potent neighbouring Prince to caſt his Eye upon us, who will not want the ſuggeſtions of Ambition and Intereſt to try his Fortune; and if he ſhould, who can withſtand him we being thus divided? Methinks the ill conſequen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces which may be foreſeen to ariſe from ſuch plain demon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrations of a divided Nation, ſhould prevail upon the moſt tender Conſcience, not to be guilty of any thing that brings ſuch certain ruine to his King, Country, and Proteſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ant
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:93024:10"/> Religion; eſpecially having Liberty according to Law, to exerciſe his Religion in his own way, in his own houſe, with his own family, and an addition under Five more; which indeed is too great a kindneſs, and more than they will ever deſerve?</p>
               <p>If a Kingdom can be ſafe, when it has perſons in it that<note place="margin">Sir William Smiths Speech, Apr. 24. 1682.</note> confederate for the mutual aſſiſtance of each other, upon all occaſions, when they will ſpare no pains or coſt for the advancement of each others Intereſt, when they ſcarce trade with any other but themſelves, and have no manner of commerce with any of the Church Party, or any Loyal man. If to ſet up a Commonwealth in a Kingdom is ſafe, I deſire they may enjoy themſelves without any further mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſtation; but if not, if on theſe accounts, we are in very dangerous conditions, we muſt apply our ſelves to the Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>medies, to the due and ſtrict Execution of the Laws to pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vent it.</p>
               <p>You ſee I don't inſiſt upon old ſtories of 41, becauſe ſome of you have been ſo good or ſo cunning as to diſown them; whatſoever I have mentioned is almoſt at this very day to be ſeen. This is the time for Union, <hi>now or never;</hi> that <hi>great Mountain,</hi> as you are pleas'd to term it, and that pretended hinderance, (<hi>viz.</hi> the Obligation to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nounce<note place="margin">See the Act of <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nifor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mity.</note> the Solemn League and Covenant) has its end; for it was to ceaſe <hi>March</hi> 28. 1682. as you may ſee in the <hi>Act of <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>niformity.</hi> If I be not deceived, Mr. <hi>Baxter</hi> promiſed us when that time came, to throw off his Nonconformity, and convince the world that he was naturally <hi>meek and peaceable,</hi> and that it was not Obſtinacy or a blind Preju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dice that made him ſeparate from us all this while. I wiſh he would be as good as his word, and bring his Party with him, that Strife and Janglings, Seditions and Rebellions, might die amongſt us; that that <hi>
                     <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nity</hi> might be preſerv'd, which God looks upon to be his greateſt Attribute, that Men might not be forced to confeſs themſelves Chriſtans,
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:93024:11"/> that thoſe ungrateful and hard Laws might be wholly thrown by, which I am ſure the Apoſtles themſelves, if they were alive, and in our Circumſtances, would make uſe of.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Prejud.</speaker>
               <p>You are extreamly out of the way, they are the only Chriſtians in the Nation; Popery had long ago come in upon us, had not their <hi>Pious, Godly</hi> Zeal oppos'd it; though you maliciouſly aver, that it will never pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vail, unleſs it take Presbytery in it's hand, unleſs a Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venticle covers it: but all this while you have ſpent your Forces againſt ſeditious Meetings, againſt the Perſons that ſeparate from the Church, and yet you have as real Enemies that lye unſeen in your own Boſoms. As you told me here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tofore that there were <hi>Popiſh Tories</hi> and <hi>Protestant Tories,</hi> ſo I find there are <hi>Conventicle Whiggs</hi> and <hi>Church Whiggs;</hi> theſe latter (though conforming to the Ceremonies of the Church, and ſwallowing down every thing that is given to them) being as averſe to the Government as the former. Wherefore, ſince the bare Execution of the Laws againſt Conventicles does in no wiſe reach them, or will ſtop their Mouths, ſince you pretend to be ſo good and skillful in Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pedients and Remedies, I deſire to be ſatisfied what your Art and Policy would be pleas'd to preſcribe in this Caſe.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Reaſ.</speaker>
               <p>Truly theſe are dangerous Enemies, and make us think them to be ſo, and be the more concerned, <hi>becauſe they are of our own Houſhold.</hi> I am amaz'd at a profeſs'd Knave, an impudent, bare-fac'd Hypocrite, nay one that tells us himſelf, though he <hi>embraces</hi> with one hand, he will <hi>ſtab</hi> with the other.</p>
               <p>It would be look'd upon as Injuſtice and Arbitrary Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vernment, if ſuch a Law was enacted Now, as was hereto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore in <hi>Rome,</hi> hindering private Cabals, reſtraining all <hi>Ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vern-Politicians;</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Sueton.</note> but they muſt thank themſelves, if we fly to the utmoſt extremity of Juſtice, rather than ſuffer our ſelves to be <hi>baſely</hi> undone. But ſince we cannot force them to a compliance, ſince they are ſo <hi>maliciouſly</hi> wiſe, and
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:93024:11"/> underſtand themſelves ſo far, as to ſin within an <hi>hairs breadth</hi> of the Law, and come within an inch of Treaſon, let us try if Arguments will ſignifie any thing with theſe <hi>white</hi> and <hi>black</hi> Traytors, theſe <hi>giddy Republicans,</hi> if ſpreading their Errours before their Eyes will make them ſee their <hi>no-Intereſt</hi> and <hi>Folly.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>We know (that beſides their little Cavils and Pecks at<note place="margin">See the 1ſt part of this Dialogue.</note> the Ceremonies and Conſtitutions of the Church (which we have in our former Diſcourſe vindicated) that their two grand Topicks are, whether a Free State (as they call it) or a <hi>Commonwealth</hi> is not more convenient and more to be deſir'd than <hi>Monarchy.</hi> And ſecondly, Whether a Popiſh Succeſſor, or a Succeſſor that does not pleaſe the humour of the People, for certain Miſdemeanours, cannot be Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cluded? or, (which is almoſt the ſame) whether <hi>England</hi> is not an Elective Kingdom? I ſhall not be over curious in theſe Points, or deſire the aſſiſtance of <hi>Cobweb</hi> Antiqui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty to lead me; but whatſoever of Reaſon or Religion lyes in my way I ſhall unfold it to you, having always thought, that though a Cuſtom is never ſo ancient, that it derives it's <hi>Pedigree</hi> from <hi>Adam,</hi> yet if it is diſcovered to be ſinful and inconvenient, that no one is obliged to follow it.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Prejud.</speaker>
               <p>But to the Point, I ſay a <hi>Commonwealth</hi> is more to be deſired than <hi>Monarchy.</hi> I will argue only from the <hi>Conveniences</hi> of the one, and <hi>Inconveniences</hi> of the other.</p>
               <p n="1">1 <hi>Arg.</hi> Firſt, Monarchy profeſſes it ſelf accountable to none but God, ſo that its very Nature is inclin'd to <hi>Tyranny;</hi> whereas a Commonwealth is a Government ſtiled by all Politicians, <hi>Free.</hi> There's <hi>Venice</hi> and the <hi>
                     <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nited Provinces</hi> what Wonders have they done! The firſt having ſtood a<note place="margin">See the Plea againſt Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>narchy, prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted in the year 1652.</note> Bulwark for above a thouſand years againſt the <hi>Turk;</hi> and the latter from her Infancy a Wall to the King of <hi>Spain</hi>'s Enchroachments.</p>
               <p n="2">2 <hi>Arg.</hi> In a Monarchy, its Iſſue being married to Fo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reigners, the Crown may be transferred from one Stran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gers
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:93024:12"/> Head to another, whereas in a Commonwealth, <hi>we</hi> and <hi>our children</hi> may enjoy it.</p>
               <p n="3">3. <hi>Arg.</hi> God gave Kings to the People in his wrath, and that ſcandalous Adoration uſually given to Princes, had its beginning from the bitter root of Idolatry.</p>
               <p n="4">4 <hi>Arg.</hi> Monarchs are commonly ambitious and covetous, ungrateful, ſway'd by the fooliſhneſs of Women, and Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vourites; whereas <hi>Many</hi> are not ſo apt to be intoxicated<note place="margin">Ibid.</note> with the fumes of <hi>Power</hi> and <hi>Flattery.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="5">5 <hi>Arg.</hi> Kings are more in danger of <hi>violent</hi> Deaths; and 'tis obſerv'd in every Family, within three or four Genera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions the Heir is an abſolute Fool, whereas a <hi>Senate</hi> never <hi>dies,</hi> and is perpetually <hi>wiſe.</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Ibid.</note>
               </p>
               <p n="6">6 <hi>Arg.</hi> In a Monarchy the Kingdom may deſcend upon an <hi>Infant,</hi> and the <hi>Succeſſion</hi> may be long in diſpute, and ſo the State muſt be without Government till he comes to years and Diſcretion, whereas there is no ſuch thing in a Commonwealth.</p>
               <p>I could reckon up ſeveral more inconveniences in Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>narchy, but 'twould be tedious to you and me too to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cite them all: wherefore I ſhall onely conclude, that it is a mere Imitation and Ape of the Pope, the one being <hi>Vicar General</hi> for things Temporal, the other for Eternal.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Reaſ.</speaker>
               <p>That's onely a little Rhetorick, for Kings and Monarchy was before ever the Pope, or his pretended Pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deceſſor S. <hi>Peter,</hi> was thought of. The hopes of a ſhare in Government, and that ſilly childiſh deſire of Change, has prevailed upon you. But that I may ſhew you <hi>conve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niences in Monarchy,</hi> and <hi>inconveniences in a Commonwealth,</hi> I ſay,</p>
               <p n="1">1. In a Monarchy the <hi>private</hi> Intereſt is the ſame with the <hi>publick.</hi> The <hi>Riches, Power, Strength, Reputation</hi> of the King, ariſe onely from the <hi>Riches, &amp;c.</hi> of the Subject; for if the Subjects be poor and ſcandalous, the King muſt be ſo too. Whereas in a Commonwealth the <hi>private</hi> In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tereſt
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:93024:12"/> being ſeparated from the <hi>publick,</hi> each <hi>Senator</hi> ſhall ſnatch for himſelf and his Family, and lazily broodingover his Bags, from the <hi>miſery</hi> and <hi>leanneſs</hi> of the People grow <hi>fat</hi> and <hi>happy.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="2">2. All the conveniences that you will attribute to one General in an Army, as having no Partner, does not force his Souldiers to Diviſions, as they are not moleſted with contrary Counſels and Commands, the very ſame you may conclude in Monarchy.</p>
               <p n="3">3. There cannot be ſo much <hi>Secreſie</hi> in the Counſels of a Multitude, as there is in a Monarchy; a thing which is ſo eſſential to the preſervation of the State.</p>
               <p n="4">4. In a Commonwealth there certainly will be Diſtracti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on in Opinions, ſo that they will not help but hinder one another; and if there is no buſineſs for them abroad, they will make War amongſt themſelves, and oppoſe one ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther for particular Intereſts at home. So <hi>Venice</hi> and the <hi>
                     <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nited Provinces,</hi> (which by the by do place ſeveral things wholly in their <hi>Duke</hi> and <hi>Prince of Orange</hi>) if Acti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on had not imployed their thoughts, I dare engage would long ago have grown <hi>Plotters</hi> and <hi>miſchievous,</hi> and by a dozen years continued peace would have been undone.</p>
               <p n="5">5. A Commonwealth is more inclining to Arbitrary Power and Tyranny than Monarchy, though placed in one Man, that is mad, extravagant, fooliſh, and Popiſh; and though he profeſſes himſelf accountable to none but God. A Commonwealth is more ſubject to evil Counſellours and Flatterers, nay rather than want they will flatter by turns to ſerve each others Ambition. The Favourites and Kind<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red of Monarchs are but few, of an Aſſembly many; ſo that every one will look to be reſpected, and deſire that his Ambition and Covetouſneſs may be ſatisfied. Beſides, they too profeſs themſelves accountable to none but God; for if they have the Power in their own hands, to whom can or will they be accountable? Or, ſince they have ſo
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:93024:13"/> many Friends, who will be forced more to Ingratitude and Knavery, or have more occaſions to be Rogues than theſe?</p>
               <p n="6">6. I wonder you a Republican ſhould think it an incon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venience, that the Monarchy ſhould deſcend upon a Fool or an Infant, when for a while comes in a Council or an Aſſembly, ſo much beloved and deſired by you; from which he could not have the underſtanding to diſſent or contradict.</p>
               <p n="7">7. The Admiſſion of a Foreiner and Stranger to a King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom is not always an inconvenience; for that King <hi>James</hi> was a good Prince, that the Union of the Kingdom is an happineſs to us, every body will affirm.</p>
               <p n="8">8. Monarchs and Kings are certainly ſent by God, good or bad; the former being a bleſſing, the later a puniſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, ſent from Heaven upon a Nation. I know that 'tis very common with ſome men, to infer from 1 <hi>Sam. c.</hi> 8.<note place="margin">1 Sam. c. 8.</note> that God ſent Kings in his wrath, and as a curſe and affli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction to his People: But if theſe men are any ways incli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned to find out the Truth, they will ſee that 'twas a <hi>Bad</hi> King that God ſent in his wrath, the Government of Kings being long before in other Nations, to which <hi>Iſrael</hi> (re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jecting God for their Monarch and Guide) deſired to be like, and which provoked him to anger.</p>
               <p>And then <hi>Solomons</hi> ſaying, <hi>In the multitude of counſel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lours</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Pro. 11. 14.</note> 
                  <hi>is much ſafety,</hi> has been very often in their mouths; as if <hi>Solomon,</hi> who was himſelf a Monarch, had given ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vice that a <hi>Parliament Government</hi> and a <hi>Commonwealth</hi> was the beſt. The meaning of the words is this, that 'tis<note place="margin">M<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>ſlerus, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 word">
                        <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                     </gap>, &amp;c. Groti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>, &amp;c.</note> good and convenient, when a Monarch goes to war, to liſten to the advice of many Friends, that ſo having all things laid open, he may chooſe that which pleaſes him beſt, or is moſt neceſſary; that to proceed with diſcretion and deliberation is the moſt probable means of ſafety.</p>
               <pb n="21" facs="tcp:93024:13"/>
               <p>But after all this I do acknowledge, that there is no Government without inconveniences. Indeed I will grant you many to be in <hi>Monarchy;</hi> yet let the inconve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niences be never ſo great, I am ſure <hi>Civil Wars, Amar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chy,</hi> and <hi>Confuſion,</hi> will outweigh them all; which muſt necſſarily be in a Commonwealth, and which ſhall be the onely Anſwer I give to your Arguments.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Monarchy</hi> has the feweſt and leaſt inconveniences, is the moſt honourable, moſt exact, and moſt perfect Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vernment, as being after the example of one God, who firſt preſented us a Patern.</p>
               <p>'Tis true, if you imagine a <hi>Plato</hi>'s Commonwealth, think that there is no ſuch thing as Intereſt in the world, that every one is for the publick good, the Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vernment you plead for might ſeem ſomewhat plauſible. But whileſt Man carries Nature about him, whileſt <hi>Craft, Pride, Covetouſneſs,</hi> and the <hi>Devil</hi> is in Mankind; whileſt there is ſcarce <hi>ten righteous perſons amongſt us,</hi> to ſtop the <hi>judgment of Fire and Brimſtone</hi> on our Nation, that<note place="margin">Gen. 18.</note> falſe intoxicating Notion of <hi>Liberty</hi> that you have got, that deſire of being like <hi>beaſts in a wilderneſs,</hi> wild and uncontroul'd, that eagerneſs of a Commonwealth Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vernment, muſt neceſſarily caſt us into ruine and deſtru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Prejud.</speaker>
               <p>But all this while I am for a Commonwealth. Now let us conſider whether <hi>England</hi> is not an Elective Kingdom, whether the true Heir or lawful Succeſſor, if not pleaſing to the People, cannot be diſinherited. Let us conſider, Firſt, the <hi>Legality,</hi> and the <hi>Practice</hi> of anci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ent times. Secondly, the <hi>Equity</hi> of it, and the unrea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſonableneſs of a contrary Doctrine.</p>
               <p n="1">
                  <label>1 <hi>Arg.</hi>
                  </label> As to the <hi>Legality</hi> and <hi>Practice</hi> of former times, I could tell you ſtories from <hi>Egbert</hi> down to <hi>Mary</hi> Queen of <hi>Scots;</hi> ſo that I don't queſtion but every one
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:93024:14"/> will make Obſervations from it, that it has been the conſtant Opinion of all Ages, that the Parliament of <hi>England</hi> had an unqueſtionable power to elect, limit, re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrain, and qualifie the Succeſſion as they pleaſe, and that on all occaſions they have put their power in practice; and that the <note n="*" place="margin">Daniel, Hen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry I.</note> Hiſtorian had reaſon for ſaying, that <hi>Seldom or never the third Heir in a right deſcent enjoyed the Crown of England.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="2">
                  <label>2 <hi>Arg.</hi>
                  </label> As to the <hi>Equity,</hi> and unreaſonableneſs of a contrary Doctrine; I ſay it tends directly to ſubvert the Government, and to put the Life of the King regnant in the hands of the Succeſſor. The next Heir may com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mit Rapes, Murders, and Treaſons, burn Cities, betray<note place="margin">Hiſtory of Suc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſion for the Earl of H.</note> Fleets, may conſpire againſt the Life of his Prince; and yet after all if he can by flight or force ſave himſelf, till ſome of his Accomplices can get the King diſpatch'd, in ſpight of all Laws and Juſtice he muſt come to the Crown and be innocent.</p>
               <p>Though <hi>paſſive obedience,</hi> and the forgiving of <hi>pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vate</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Tory Plot.</note> 
                  <hi>injuries,</hi> is laudable; yet Offenders and Offences againſt the <hi>Government</hi> are of another nature and conſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deration.</p>
               <p>In caſe of Minority, Madneſs, Folly, the tryal of the Kings Sufficiency, is without queſtion in the Parliament. And if that be allowed, ſhall wicked and contumacious<note place="margin">Plea for Ele<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctive Kingdom.</note> Principles and Practiſes be exempt from their cogni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zance; ſince the Fool or Madman cannot be lyable to ſo ſevere a Cenſure, as he that imploys his wit to the de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtruction of the People?</p>
               <p>The Crown is not a bare Inheritance, but an Inherit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ance<note place="margin">Hiſtory of Suc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſion, Ibid.</note> accompanying an Office of Truſt; ſo that if any mans Defects render him uncapable of the Truſt, he has forfeited his Inheritance.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <pb n="23" facs="tcp:93024:14"/>
               <speaker>Reaſ.</speaker>
               <p>To the firſt Argument I anſwer, Firſt, though the diſinheriting a true Heir was the Practice of ſome of our Anceſtours; yet from thence it does not follow, 'twas legally and lawfully practiſed, for (as you have heard ſeveral times) Though a thing has been <hi>often</hi> done, it is not therefore <hi>well</hi> done. <hi>Cromwel</hi>'s Uſurpa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion will not juſtifie another hereafter; neither ought the late <hi>High Court of Juſtice</hi> to be a Patern and Model to Poſterity how to erect the like. Now whether the Precedents of our Forefathers were <hi>equitable</hi> or <hi>righte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous,</hi> comes under your ſecond Head, where you pretend to ſhew the Equity of it, and the unreaſonableneſs of a contrary Doctrine, to which I ſhall ſpeak anon.</p>
               <p>But a while to the <hi>Legality</hi> of it. I am ſure we can ſhew more Precedents of Kings holding their Crowns by right of Primogeniture, than they can to the contrary; it being deſired by moſt Monarchs of the Chriſtian and Heathen World, though ſometimes a Factious and Diſloy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>al Party grows to be ſo numerous, as to bilk them in their Endeavours. And though we cannot determine who is the neareſt in the Family, in a long Line of Suc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſion; (as ſometimes I have heard you object) yet whom we think in our Conſciences to be the perſon, we muſt ſubmit to him as if he were the real true one.</p>
               <p>The Bond of <hi>Allegiance,</hi> (whether ſworn or not ſworn to) being, as it were a Law of Nature, perpetual and indiſpenſable, ſhews the Illegality, which, though per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>haps it may not oblige us to Succeſſors in the Life-time of our preſent Sovereign, yet at his Death it certainly enjoyns us to ſee him ſafe in the Throne, to look upon him as <hi>true</hi> Heir and <hi>lawful</hi> Succeſſor, being the Iſſue of the deceaſed Sovereign, and not to joyn with an equi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vocating Party, who do interpret the Oath of <hi>Allegiance</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Tory Plot.</note> to mean him to be the <hi>Lawful</hi> Succeſſor, whom a diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>contented
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:93024:15"/> ſort of People are pleaſed to call ſo, or ſet up.</p>
               <p>Beſides, though we ſhould grant that 'twas the Pra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctice of our Anceſtors to legitimate and illegitimate as they pleaſe, that they had the Power to <hi>Elect, Limit, Reſtrain,</hi> or Qualifie as they thought convenient, you will agree with us, that 'twas by the Conſent of King, Lords and Commons, or in caſe the King was dead, of Lords and Commons; why how is this appli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cable to the caſe of the <hi>D.</hi> of <hi>Y.</hi> where there was on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly the ſingle Votes of the Commons, which never were perfect Laws, or had the ſame force by themſelves, as if the King and Lords had conſented with them? The King and Lords rejected the Bill, and above the third part of the Nation thanked them for it; wherefore I con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clude that the Practiſes of our Anceſtors are nothing to the purpoſe, and your beloved Hiſtory of Succeſſion (written for the ſatisfaction of the Earl of <hi>H.</hi> but confu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted ſufficiently already) and your Stories from <hi>Egbert</hi> to <hi>Mary</hi> Queen of <hi>Scots,</hi> by this to be utterly confounded.</p>
               <p>But if you do ask me, Whether, if the K. ſhould dye, I think the Lords and Commons would do the feat? I anſwer no otherwiſe, but that 'tis a vain thing to imagine it <hi>will</hi> or <hi>can</hi> ever be done, ſeeing the former too dai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly proteſt againſt it, nay, and <hi>S.</hi> himſelf begins to recant.</p>
               <p>Now that the King and Lords had Equity on their ſides in ſo doing, that the Doctrine, though contrary to yours, is not unreaſonable; I ſhall ſhew by giving full Anſwers to your Arguments.</p>
               <p>To the ſecond Argument. Though I grant your Sup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſition, that the next Heir ſhould commit Rapes, Mur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ders, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> were mad and fooliſh, I ſay, 'tis not in the Power of the Houſe of Commons to exclude him from the Crown, neither can there be ſhewn one Precedent
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:93024:15"/> that they may imitate, ſeeing 'twas alwayes allow'd that the Houſe of Lords had as much, or more Authority than they, and the King a Negative Voice. Neither doth this tend to the Subverſion of the Government, if this irregular Heir ſhould come to the Crown, but rather to the eſtabliſhment of it, it taking away any Succeſs that the the ſcandalous and unjuſt imputations of a giddy Rabble might make for the future upon one that is innocent. If <hi>Im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moralities</hi> and <hi>Crimes</hi> would do the buſineſs, a <hi>preſent</hi> Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>narch would not want Enemies that ſhould aſperſe and depoſe him.</p>
               <p>The Doctrine of Paſſive Obedience ought to be em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>braced by the <hi>publick</hi> as well as the <hi>private,</hi> for though I agree with you, it may not be obſerv'd in reſpect to Fo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reign Affronts and Abuſes, yet Subjects ought to obſerve it in reſpect to their Prince, being at all no diſhonour to the State.</p>
               <p>And though I grant you too that a Crown is an In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>heritance accompanying an Office of Truſt, yet I cannot yield that a Houſe of Commons, nay, if they were joyn'd with the Houſe of Lords too, the King declaring to the contrary, are capable Judges, whether the Heir can be defective of that Truſt, or forfeit his Inheritance. And though he were really defective, Mad, and of ill Prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciples, they muſt for all that ſubmit, and bear with him; his <hi>Power</hi> being as much the <hi>Ordinance</hi> of <hi>God,</hi> as the Power of the wiſeſt, beſt Prince in the World. Theſe are but Subjects to the King, while living, or to his <hi>lawful Heir,</hi> when dead, (by which <hi>lawful,</hi> you muſt think Natural Affection meant the neareſt of Blood) and in them to be placed the Sovereign Power. Now if the two Houſes could diſpoſe of this Sovereign Pow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er, you muſt think they had as great or greater in themſelves, than the Sovereign or higheſt Power; which to affirm is Nonſenſe.</p>
               <pb n="26" facs="tcp:93024:16"/>
               <p>The King hath his Authority from God, and to him<note place="margin">Sir William Smiths Speech.</note> alone he is accountable: He hath the Laws only from his People, by which he ought to govern, which <hi>Laws</hi> you Diſſenters miſtake for the <hi>Authority.</hi> The King therefore ought not to be importun'd by the People to do any thing contrary to what he judges lawful, for he alone muſt anſwer for the irregularities, not they.</p>
               <p>But to go a little farther with the Equity of it. Do<note place="margin">Ibid.</note> you think it reaſonable, that a man ſhould be puniſh'd <hi>in praeſenti,</hi> for a fault to be committed <hi>in futuro?</hi> If a Bill had been preſented to a Grand Jury againſt a Man, upon preſumption he would commit ſuch or ſuch a Crime a year hence, ſurely they would never find the Bill. This of the <hi>D.</hi> of <hi>Y.</hi> is of the ſame nature. His being a Papiſt cannot be a fault, until he was to ſucceed to the Crown, and that is uncertain whether ever or never. But if God hath made an Election, it is not for you to ſay, <hi>Nolumus hunc regnare.</hi> It would be to que<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtion Divine Wiſdom and uſurp upon Gods Preroga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tive, in whoſe hands are the iſſues of Life and Death, and all other Events, to which all men in prudence ought to ſubmit, becauſe they know they muſt do it whether they will or no. Fears and jealouſies ought not to make People extravagant. Diſputes of Succeſſion are dangerous. The controverſie between the Houſe of <hi>Y.</hi> and <hi>Lancaſter</hi> had almoſt drown'd us in our own Blood, if the Good God in his infinite Mercy at laſt had not relieved us.</p>
               <p>I cannot ſee why People ſhould be ſo deſirous of an Elective Kingdom, ſeeing <hi>Diſorder</hi> in the mean while muſt tyrannize; and ſeeing Burgeſſes, Aldermen, and Mayors of little Corporations cannot be choſe without Tumult, Noiſe and Confuſion, an unanimous Conſent being ſeldom or never heard of amongſt them.</p>
               <pb n="27" facs="tcp:93024:16"/>
               <p>We murdered and depoſed the <hi>Royal Father,</hi> and we have ſeemed to repent in duſt and aſhes, cried mightily, and requeſted of Heaven that <hi>the ſin might not be laid to our charge, that the bitter cup might paſs from us;</hi> and ſhall we be ſo impudent and ungretefully wicked, as to murther him again in his <hi>Posterity?</hi> We ſhall not be ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cuſed at the great day, becauſe we have <hi>perſiſted</hi> in our iniquity, neither will God be <hi>frighted</hi> into a forgive<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs. 'Tis their right, and nothing but an immediate Voice from Heaven can make it otherwiſe.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Prejud.</speaker>
               <p>
                  <hi>Electing</hi> and <hi>Excluding</hi> had been practiſed by Gods own People, and countenanced by God. What elſe is the meaning of Gods giving the Kingdom of <hi>Iſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rael</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Tory Plot.</note> to <hi>Saul</hi> of the Tribe of <hi>Benjamin,</hi> the youngeſt of <hi>Jacob</hi>'s Sons; or to <hi>David</hi> the younger of his Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers Sons, and of the Tribe of <hi>Judah;</hi> while none of <hi>Reuben</hi>'s Of-ſpring ever ſate upon the Throne? Or if God may by <hi>Prerogative</hi> diſpence with this Law, how came <hi>David</hi> to put <hi>Adonijah</hi> by the Throne, and ſeat <hi>Solomon</hi> in it?</p>
               <p>After <hi>Solomon</hi> there was not one bad Prince longer endured, than the People were conſtrained out of mere neceſſity: to whoſe deſtruction alſo they were oftentimes incited by God himſelf.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Reaſ.</speaker>
               <p>Your own Author in two or three Leaves after confutes himſelf, and tells you the Commands and Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>amples in the Old Teſtament, cannot countenance ſuch an Aſſertion, nor can the Civil Conſtitutions of the <hi>Jew<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iſh</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Tory Plot.</note> Oeconomy oblige any Chriſtian Kingdoms, there be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing very ſpecial Reaſons to the contrary. As God had a ſpecial Prerogative for giving his Kingdom of <hi>Iſrael</hi> to <hi>Saul,</hi> ſo had <hi>David</hi> too, when he excluded <hi>Adonijah</hi> and gave the Kingdom to <hi>Solomon,</hi> it being by the im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mediate direction of God himſelf. But now God for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bearing
<pb n="28" facs="tcp:93024:17"/> to ſpeak to us immediately from Heaven, ſends us word, that <hi>The fear of a King is as the roaring of a Lion:</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Prov. 20. 2.</note> 
                  <hi>whoſo provoketh him to anger, ſinneth againſt his own ſoul. That we ſhould not touch his anointed, nor do his Prophets harm. Speak thou to us, and we will hear thee; but let</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Exod. 20. 19.</note> 
                  <hi>not God ſpeak to us leſt we die.</hi> This is a moſt abſolute obedience to <hi>Moſes.</hi> Concerning the Right of Kings God ſpeaketh by the mouth of <hi>Samuel,</hi> and ſaith, <hi>This</hi>
                  <note place="margin">1 Sam. 8. 11, 12, &amp;c.</note> 
                  <hi>will be the right of the King which you ſhall have to reign over you; he ſhall take your ſons, and ſet them to drive chariots, &amp;c. He ſhall take your man-ſervants and your maid-ſervants, and the choice of your youth, and imploy them in his buſineſs, &amp;c.</hi> So that whatſoever he will inflict on you, it muſt by no means be reſiſted. But let us hear what the Goſpel ſays, <hi>The Scribes and Phariſees</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Mat. 23. 2, 3.</note> 
                  <hi>ſit in Moſes chair, and therefore all that they ſhall bid you do and obſerve, that obſerve and do.</hi> Where can there be a more ſimple Obedience implied, and what can com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mand Subjection more plainly? <hi>Submit your ſelves to every ordinance of man for the Lords ſake, for conſcience ſake.</hi> I know that grand Impoſtor and Mountebank <hi>Bu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chanan,</hi> with his Zany <hi>Milton,</hi> explain theſe places as if they were ſpoken to the <hi>ſcattered</hi> and <hi>weak</hi> Chriſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ans, that they ſhould be ſubject out of <hi>policy,</hi> becauſe they had not <hi>opportunity</hi> and <hi>ſtrength</hi> to reſiſt. But it ſeems very ſtrange to me, that if common prudence one<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly and ſelf-preſervation were in the caſe, that the Apoſtle ſhould urge it with ſo much vehemency and extrava<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gance, that they ſhould be deſired to <hi>live</hi> for the <hi>Lords ſake,</hi> and for <hi>conſcience ſakc,</hi> when afterwards they ſo eagerly ſtrove to <hi>die</hi> for it.</p>
               <p>Is there not plain poſitive Practice conſonant to theſe Doctrines? Did not Chriſt, as ſoon as he was ſeiz'd on by the High Prieſts Officers, ſeverely rebuke the great
<pb n="29" facs="tcp:93024:17"/> Apoſtle St. <hi>Peter,</hi> for but once uſing the Sword? Blame an untemperate Zeal, proceeding from an unreaſonable Paſſion, without any Call to his Superiours? Chide him for wounding the High Prieſts Servant, though he was performing a moſt unjuſt action; but, he being com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſſioned by Publick Authority, taught, that every Pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vate Mam muſt ſubmit to him? Will you think too that Chriſt did this out of policy, becauſe he was too weak to ſtruggle with them? No, he tells you, he could have fummon'd more than <hi>twelve Legions of Angels to his im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mediate reſcue.</hi> But he would not employ them as a tri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>umphant<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Dr.</hi> Sprat, <hi>Serm. Ap. 20. 12.</hi>
                  </note> Hoſt, but as an Harmonious Choir, to <hi>ſing peace on Earth, good will towards every one of you.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>If it is then forbidden on the Penalty of Death, of <hi>periſhing by the Sword,</hi> to rebell againſt thoſe moſt cruel Tyrants, moſt fierce Enemies to the Chriſtians, Mon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſters of men, either of no Religion, or a falſe one, and yet a diſgrace to Heatheniſm it ſelf; If however, on the moſt Solemn Obligations of Conſcience, they were not to be oppos'd, much leſs deſtroy'd by any Chriſtians; what can be ſaid greater, or more auguſt than this? What ſtronger, what more Sacred confirmation can be given to our conſcientious obedience to <hi>another manner</hi> of Authority? By how many tyes, Temporal and Eter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nal, are we bound to yield a faithful Subjection to our Chriſtian Kings? under whoſe Protection many Subjects proſper, though againſt their Wills; Kings, who are the beſt nurſing Fathers of the beſt Church in the Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtian World.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Prejud.</speaker>
               <p>Chriſt and his Diſciples might well bear with this; <hi>for their Kingdom was not of this world. They came</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Joh. 18. 36. Charge of the Tory Plot maintain'd.</note> 
                  <hi>not to divide Inheritances.</hi> Which rather implies than denies, that ſuch whoſe Kingdom is of this World <hi>may</hi> diſpoſe of Inheritances.</p>
               <pb n="30" facs="tcp:93024:18"/>
               <p>
                  <hi>Reaſ.</hi> Truly the Chriſtians Kingdom too is not of this world, for if it were, <hi>they would be of all men the most miſerable.</hi> They came to imitate Chriſt, to <hi>ſubmit to every Ordinance of Man</hi> as he did, to bear afflictions, to follow him through a Sea of Bloud, though 'twere tho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>row the wilderneſs of Popery, and moſt ſevere inconve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nienees.</p>
               <p>There is not a Vertue in the whole Life of our Savi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>our<note place="margin">Mr. Manning<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hams Sermon, Dec. 7.</note> propoſed to our imitation, which has not for its Ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pendage that which the <hi>Animal man</hi> calls Miſery; tho' it proves in the event, the onely winging of the Soul, the higheſt <hi>exaltation of humane nature,</hi> which had never been honoured with the <hi>
                     <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nion of God,</hi> if it had not been in order to <hi>ſuffer.</hi>
               </p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Prejud.</speaker>
               <p>'Tis a good thing in <hi>private</hi> men to bear Affli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctions patiently, not to run into an evil to avoid them, to glory in their tribulation. But when, Sir, the State is concerned, when the queſtion is, whether they muſt ſuffer a Popiſh Tyrant to reign over them when they can-hinder it, they will tell you they don't think them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves bound to ſuch <hi>narrow, private</hi> Apprehenſions of things, neither will <hi>State Policy</hi> allow of ſuch directions as <hi>paſſive obedience</hi> would give them. They will not<note place="margin">Spec. Crape. part 2.</note> call thoſe things evil which you may. A Captain of a <hi>Man of War</hi> being like to be taken by the Enemy, is bound to ſink his Ship, and blow up it may be three or four hundred men, rather than deliver his Charge to the Enemy. One would think it an evil in it ſelf to de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtroy ſo many innocent Souls; yet unleſs this be done, the Captain ſhall be ſhot to death by the Laws of War, and look'd upon as an Enemy.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Reaſ.</speaker>
               <p>Suppoſe I do grant in ſome ſpecial caſes, that <hi>State Policy</hi> ought not to call thoſe things evil which private men do, (as requiring ſatisfaction for injuries
<pb n="31" facs="tcp:93024:18"/> offer'd by a Forein Kingdom, which I hinted to you be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore;) how does this excuſe Subjects from committing an evil againſt their Prince, who are commanded <hi>as Sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jects</hi> to bear with him, and obey him.</p>
               <p>Then your Inſtance in a Captain of a Man of War, does not hold true, for 'tis ſeldom or never practis'd, that he ſhall be ſhot to death, if he is in thoſe circumſtan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces, and unleſs he is under ſuſpicion of Treachery. Nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther ought he upon any account to ſink the ſhip, or de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtroy ſo many innocent Souls; and if he is puniſhed for the Non-performance of it, his Puniſhment is ſevere and unjuſt? Religion binds us not only to our <hi>Perſonal</hi> Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pacities, but as to our <hi>Relative</hi> and <hi>Politick</hi> too, as we are incorporated into Kingdoms, Families, and other So<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cieties.<note place="margin">Dr. Wallis, S. Reſurrection aſſerted.</note> As Societies are made up of ſingle Perſons, ſo the acts of Societies, and of Perſons related, whether ſin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful or virtuous, are in <hi>Gods account</hi> the Acts of parti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cular Perſons; and are in thoſe Perſons puniſhed and rewarded according to their Deſerts, both in this World and in that which is to come. And thus the Ci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties of <hi>Sodom</hi> and <hi>Gomorrah,</hi> with thoſe about them, are ſaid to ſuffer the Vengeance of Eternal Fire, when indeed it is the <hi>Perſons</hi> of thoſe Cities that do ſuffer. Theſe are the words of a Learned man, who is ſaid to be a well-wiſher to your Party, but I hope he is be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lied.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Prejud.</speaker>
               <p>If we muſt bear every thing <hi>as Subjects,</hi> that is inflicted upon us, if we cannot chuſe the Perſon to reign over us, where is the Liberty of the Subject all this while?</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Reaſon.</speaker>
               <p>What, will you commit Treaſon, and plead the Liberty of the Subject? Have you not free Trade, free liberty to buy and ſell, to chuſe your own Habita<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, your own Diet, your own Calling and Profeſſion,
<pb n="32" facs="tcp:93024:19"/> educate your own Children as you think fit, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> If any thing is to be decided between the Sovereign and Sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jects, is there not an Appeal to the Laws? Have not your Lawyers free liberty of Speech to plead for you? and does not Majeſty it ſelf condeſcend to their Judg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments? Are you loaden with Taxes? are your Eſtates taken from you, and have not you leave to take upon you ſo much Impudence and Ingratitude, as not to give one part in a hundred to him who protects all you have, and gives you your very Being, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> Is not the Government according to the Eſtabliſh'd Laws, and has not the <note n="*" place="margin">Kings Speech to the Parl. at Oxford.</note> King declared it ſhall be the Standard and meaſure oſ his Actions? You pine and murmur becauſe you cannot have the Liberty to be Rogues and Raſcals. I do certainly believe a Popiſh Plot, and, though I will be more candid than other men, as not to think there is a Presbyterian one; I am ſure you, as ſingle men, without any Combination, out-do the Papiſts in their Villanies. When any of your <hi>Herd</hi> is hurt, you, his fellow Swine, run about him, and gruntle againſt the Government, and by right or wrong reſolve to relieve him. You would take a Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>narchs Crown from his Head, and call it the Privilege of a Parliament. Thoſe that own themſelves to be but the <hi>Great Council</hi> to a Sovereign, are deſired by you not to behave themſelves as Counſellors, but like Sovereigns too.</p>
            </sp>
         </div>
         <div type="prophecy">
            <pb n="33" facs="tcp:93024:19"/>
            <head>The Propheſie of <hi>Mercurius Menippeus</hi> in the Year of our Lord 1641.</head>
            <p>
               <hi>IF the</hi> Londoners <hi>by this time have not enough of Parliament, may they ſtill conſult Images, and adore a Repreſentative; ſtill quarrel with Superſtition, and never be at reſt. They will perceive at laſt what kind of Phyſick is</hi> Reformation, <hi>and being drunk once a day. Sure all the Women in the City are with Child by</hi> Baxter <hi>and the</hi> Devil, <hi>that they ever ſince longed for</hi> Presbytery. <hi>For, were Altars Plea enough to offer up the Biſhops? Muſt good</hi> Abel <hi>ſuffer for his Sacrifice? Sure his</hi> Maſqueraded Holineſs <hi>was the</hi> Pope, <hi>and Juſtice on</hi> Ben. Harris'<hi>s Ears,</hi> Auri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cular Confeſſion. Pl———ket <hi>ſtrived to bring in Po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pery, and was executed like the Poor Aſs for drink<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing up the Town Moon. The Dunghil is ſweeter than the Jakes, and Doctor</hi> Salamanca. Caeſar'<hi>s Tragedy is beſt preſented in the</hi> Senate, <hi>and</hi> Weſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>minſter <hi>is the ready way to the</hi> Tombs. <hi>There has been none of late diſguis'd but the three laſt Parl————nts, and a Hang-man. Henceforth take heed of Vizards, though never ſo holy, though there is the Liberty of the Subject, and making a</hi> Glorious King <hi>in the caſe. 'Tis the Thiefs beſt play to kill the Judge, and the</hi> Diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſenters <hi>to rail on, and be for Excluding. What
<pb n="34" facs="tcp:93024:20"/> Wolves beſides theſe but would have tended ſuch a</hi> Ro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mulus? <hi>Such an</hi> Elias <hi>what</hi> Ravens <hi>but would have fed? A Prince whoſe goodneſs might rather fear Ido<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>latry than Injury, deſerved rather to be pray'd to than ſpit upon, made a Saint in our</hi> own Nation <hi>rather than to be ſent into</hi> Scotland. <hi>A Prince, whoſe Me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rits were ſo far above all Flatteries, that the oilieſt Courtier was as ſcandalous, as that</hi> Chymiſt, Fid<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ler, Buffoon, Painter, Rhymer, Railer, Drun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kard,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>See</hi> Abſalom <hi>and</hi> Achito<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phel, <hi>a Poem.</hi>
               </note> Glutton, Zimri; <hi>as fooliſh as thoſe</hi> Rab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſheka's <hi>of</hi> No Popiſh Succeſſor. Give the King no Money. <hi>A Prince, whoſe Innocence has taught the * whole Nation Allegiance, and made</hi> Pilk———ton<note place="margin">See the Ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dreſſes.</note> 
               <hi>a</hi> non eſt inventus <hi>Royaliſt; and kept</hi> turn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>coat, Curſe ye Meroz, Muſhroom Hickeringhil, <hi>a long time from being</hi> damn'd. <hi>A Prince, for whom</hi> Colledge <hi>and the</hi> City Charter <hi>do dye Martyrs; and for whom</hi> Tony Coop—<hi>undertook a</hi> Vindica<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion. <hi>But now, alas, poor</hi> Potapski <hi>is become Cap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tive to his Charge. The good</hi> Apoſtle <hi>converts his</hi> Gaoler; <hi>Who with the other</hi> Viper, Prince Pretty<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man, <hi>do</hi> kiſs his hand, <hi>and are innocent. For they knew he</hi> diſpoſſeſs'd <hi>ſo faſt, they could not find</hi> De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vils <hi>enough to bait him. Had</hi> Bet———I <hi>that rail'd at him, been on the Bench, or wore his Chain longer,</hi> 
               <note n="*" place="margin">according to the Story, &amp;c.</note> I will hold five Guinnies he had been Tyburn'd before Chriſtmas, <hi>and the ill look'd</hi> Dagon <hi>ſhould have fell before the</hi> Ark. <hi>'Tis a Queſtion, whether he
<pb n="35" facs="tcp:93024:20"/> is more miraculous now for curing</hi> Diſloyalty, <hi>than he will be hereafter for curing the</hi> Evil.</p>
            <p>Grant, O Lord, the King a long Life, that his years may endure throughout all generations.</p>
            <p>Let him dwell before God for ever: O pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pare thy loving Mercy and Faithfulneſs, that they may preſerve him.</p>
            <p>Defend the <hi>Duke,</hi> O Lord, and let his Enemies have no advantage againſt him, nor the wick<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed <hi>Diſſenters</hi> approach to hurt him.</p>
            <p>Open the Eyes of the three laſt Parliaments, and let them confeſs before thee, that they have done thoſe things which they ought not to have done; and left undone thoſe things, which they ought to have done; and that there was no help in them, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
            </p>
            <closer>Amen.</closer>
            <closer>So Prayeth
<signed>T. W.</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
         <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
